Ali Rana

Program/Project Manager | Data Analytics | Digital Innovation

CONTACT DETAILS

Melbourne, Australia Australian Citizen +61 (0)401 306 929

alirana@engineer.com

LinkedIn ranaalisaeed

Selected portfolio ranaalisaeed.github.io

CERTIFICATIONS

SAFe 4 Practitioner (Scaled Agile)

Managing Successful Programs (MSP) Practitioner, Axelos

Machine Learning (ML), Coursera

PRINCE2 Foundation, Axelos

ITILv3 Foundation, Axelos

Lean Six Sigma, Motorola Univ.

QUALIFICATIONS

Managers Advancement Program (**DMAP**), Deakin Univ.

Agile Software Development MOOC, ETH Zurich

MS Electrical Engineering National Univ. of Sciences & Technology

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Project/Program Management
- Essential SAFe
- DevSecOps
- Digital Prototyping
- Data Design & Governance
- Data Analytics
- DataViz & Dashboards
- Cloud Architecture
- Mobile & Web Development
- Lean Startups
- Process Automation

CAREER PROFILE

Project management and technology solutions professional with over 18 years of experience delivering high-visibility projects and programs. Served in various leadership and consulting roles. Adaptable experience across systems thinking, governance, user voice, product advocacy, change enablement, and data science. Working collegially and collaboratively, achieved positive outcomes for clients throughout the lifecycle of projects and programs, from conception and planning, to design, development, operations and benefits realisation.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Learning analytics app including Angular frontend, Nest JS backend, MongoDB and Extract Transform Load (ETL) pipelines.
- Database design for student engagement statistics on Hadoop Big Data platform. NiFi ingestion and HIVE storage. Data streams joined & processed using SQL/Python/Spark.
- OWASP Top Ten Security evaluation and Privacy Impact Assessment (PIA) for learning analytics initiative at Deakin.
- Delivered governance framework for Cloud Campus program (40+ initiatives). Continuous Alignment, Risk Management, Stakeholder Engagement & Communications.
- Splunk and ML Proof-of-concept (PoC) trial to detect 'contract cheating' in online exams. Anomaly detection from patterns of normal usage using Splunk and network access logs.
- Feasibility, Risk, Privacy implications assessment for university's strategy towards Analytics for Learning and Employability.
- Full stack delivery of cloud timetabling web app including schema design, API endpoints, cloud architecture and SSO integration.
- Robotic Process Automation (RPA) trial using Selenium. 'Robot' chasing missing documents from course applicants.
- Information Architecture to streamline organisation wide handling of cloud cohort data. Data Definition, Governance, Management, Compliance.
- Delivered multiple projects up to US\$ 25M on time, to expectations, within budget and scope, including an award winning TD-LTE end-to-end integration over live network. Won Gold Medal outperforming project financial KPIs and cost-saving targets.
- PoC pilot on Telco customer experience management using data analytics, securing over US\$ 4M to deliver the first commercial showcase in the country.
- Awarded appreciation by client CEO for recovering a 480 sites LTE rollout project using war-room delivery, agile techniques and launching ahead of target.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

ANALYTICS & INNOVATION MANAGER, CLOUD LEARNING

MAR 2020 - DEC 2021

DEAKIN UNIVERSITY, AUSTRALIA (www.deakin.edu.au)

- Delivered **fast-paced projects** embracing innovative lean practises. Utilised **data analytics** extensively providing insights and points of leverage for organisational decision making.
- Provided consulting and subject matter advice to executives and led several self organising multi-disciplinary teams creating new apps and use cases solving targeted business problems.
- Conceptualised and delivered Learning Analytics for Teachers web app co-designed with end-users.
 Visualisations using Syncfusion Angular components through MongoDB. App data acquired through multiple sources (incl. LMS, SMS), processed in Cloudera Data Platform, and ETL pipelines in Python/Spark. OWASP Top Ten Security controls. Most successful Learning Analytics breakthrough within Deakin building academic trust in data. Growing community of academic champions.
- Developed full stack Cloud Timetabling web app through data-informed current state analysis, rapid prototyping and human-centred design (HCD) kit. App architected as Angular frontend, NestJs backend, MySQL DB and dockerized container hosted on AWS. Successful trial in 300 units and 15K cloud students. All faculties sought this new approach to timetabling to be expanded to the whole of the university. Expansion roadmap prepared for DVC-Education.

PROGRAM & INFORMATION MANAGER, CLOUD CAMPUS

MAR 2018 - MAR 2020

DEAKIN UNIVERSITY, AUSTRALIA (www.deakin.edu.au)

- Responsible for Program Management & Governance Framework to deliver 40+ initiatives in Cloud Campus Team Plan. Established Agile practises that allowed reflective delivery with a line-of-sight to end-users. Lean templates, Canvas, Project on a Page. Resource Management with multi dimension skills mapping and integrated RAG Risk/Issue Management.
- Established several facets of Data Governance (MDM, Data Quality, Analytics) and Data Management
 for Cloud Campus cohort and streamlined its Information Architecture across the university. Engaged
 divisions and faculties to educate, configured systems and internal reports for compliance and
 accurate cohort metrics. Supported Cloud Campus team's operational/strategic decision making.
- Appointed additional duties of (Acting) Director, Cloud Campus leading a team of 17 diverse Subject Matter Experts in Cloud Service Design.
- Responding to COVID Pandemic, led a multi-disciplinary taskforce to enact a dedicated website for international students with tailored resources and support to commence their studies online.
- Partnered with faculties to deliver **MBA Course Site** and **Digital Law Clinic** concepts using **Dual-Track Innovation** process that helped shift team's focus to be more agile, reflective and user-driven.
- Offered Analytics as a Service to faculties, jointly conducting data PoC's providing useful, and otherwise hard to obtain, data to transition education to online mode.

CONSULTANT PROJECT MANAGER

MAR 2016 - FEB 2018

IMA MANAGEMENT AND TECHNOLOGY, AUSTRALIA (www.ima-mt.com)

- Designed and delivered a new landing hub (DeakinSync) for cloud students. New PHP website, with a simpler look and relevant experience tailored for online learners. Home for Cloud Campus for years to come. Resolved outstanding technical debt. Documentation for secure operation & maintenance.
- Led and delivered AU\$ 400K project to enhance Recognition for Prior Learning (RPL) system through a
 new Precedence DB, university-wide process and an online form. Security & Risk Assessment,
 Solution Architecture, Compliance and Business Feasibility for new platform, ServiceNow. Team of 10
 in a matrix environment.
- Led the transition of IBM Watson, a Machine Learning platform, to answer students' questions from the new Deakin website. With a team of 12, Watson Corpus and Ground Truth re-built (ingest, map, train) while BAU operations maintained @15K conversations per day.
- Assessed the problem of low response rates impacting Unit Evaluation Surveys. Evaluations options
 and delivered quick-win solutions. Prepared Roadmap recommendations report from holistic scan of
 the environment, systems, people and processes, engaging stakeholders.

PROJECT MANAGEMENT & SERVICE DELIVERY

DEC 2011 - DEC 2015

HUAWEI TECHNOLOGIES, BAHRAIN (www.huawei.com/en/)

 Responsible for Lead-to-Cash business engagement model (concept to launch, order to deliver, and problem to repair) for VIVA Operator (US\$ 200M revenue in 2014). Interfaced with client CXO's and Senior Managers and increased vendor satisfaction KPI by 7% (results of 3rd party survey designed to evaluate delivery quality).

WIRELESS CELLULAR NETWORKS ROLLOUT & TECHNICAL SUPPORT

DEC 2004 - NOV 2011

NOKIA SIEMENS NETWORKS & MOTOROLA INC. (BAHRAIN & PAKISTAN) (www.nokia.com)

- Implemented systems and processes for 24x7 Technical Support on-site/off-site. Cross domain team of Subject Matter Experts. Achieved five nines (99.999%) network availability.
- **Cost savings** over US\$ 2.5M negotiating back-to-back support contracts with 20+ **Third Party Vendors** supporting the network without compromising Quality and SLA KPI Performance.
- Installed, commissioned, deployed hundreds of cellular radio, core and transmission sites as part of **telco rollouts** in multiple countries. Conducted Disaster Recovery drills.

COMMON TOOLKIT

Projects Atlassian suite, GitLab, SharePoint, MS Project, MS Office advanced

Visual Design Sketch App, InVision, Adobe Creative Cloud, Miro

Digital Prototyping AWS, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Angular, NodeJS, MongoDB, MySQL, Strapi

Data Science D3js, Tableau, Python, R, scikit-learn, RapidMiner, PowerBI

ModellingDraw.io, Camunda Modeller, Visio, DBSchemaAutomationRobotFramework, VBA, VSCode, Selenium

REFERENCE

References available on request.